how often do you ever just put something
out there just to see if the tools work
rather than if the content is meaningful
fairly often yeah not so fairly often I
mean it's fun for you right yeah I mean
Twitter is entertainment I mean as much
as information so but the way I would
frame it is to say it's a a/b testing so
I mean it's basically just another word
for what you said but I do put things
out and say oh I have a theory about
this one that I think this one will go
back Niq or we're talking about content
well they're inseparable your content is
part of the technique okay right but if
I put something out there that's got all
kinds of technique I do watch it to see
if I was right and so for example a
typical viral tweet would be something
that's in the news that day something
that people are really talking about so
there's something about it that makes
people talk and then you you make a
clever connection or a joke sometimes
connecting it to something else they're
talking about like if you could tie you
know impeachment to the State of the
Union in a clever way or anything the
people just recognize that is humor and
they laugh so when I put those kinds out
they're very formulaic and those are the
ones I watched the most because I'm
seeing if the formula still works
interesting and it does and it still
works it's very consistent Americans
yeah and by the way we met you Jack
pasaba k-- yeah I don't know if he
thinks of it this way but he has so much
technique in his tweets it's not a
coincidence that they do well yeah well
I'm saying jack has been on fire and
I've watched him go from you know some
sort of five figure number of followers
just transitioning away from doing
nothing but gameofthrones tweets into
becoming a powerhouse in the media
universe and and a White House favorite
and to the you know in drawing the ire
of every
about the political journalists in
America they just can't stand that guy
and I think it's better because he
always looks like he's enjoying himself
well he is means he's having the best of
his life I can imagine he's living in
such a good life and I'm proud of him
and really happy to see that was there
was there a formula or something that
did work for you before that has died
and is there is there like a hmm if you
know if you come to market with a
product and everybody comes to mark with
the same product that kind of dilutes
the value is there has there been a
technique that that worked that that has
been extinguished because it just been
trampled by other people or well there
are some things to get overused the the
one that I'm watching now is and I've
used it a number of times because it's
always funny narrator voice if you do a
tweet you just say narrator :
whatever you say after narrator is
almost always going to be funny it's
just it's one of those formulas that
almost always works
yeah how I've been I've been trying to
get funnier Scott and it's not really
working for me I've even read books on
how to be funny and it's interesting
because there's there are formulas there
is a technique to it and there are
structures that that work time and time
and time again and one of them is using
the character right as if you present a
character saying something then that
character has one or two characteristics
and they just whatever they say or do
matches with those characteristics
people tend to think that that's really
funny it's just like a program that hits
in people's brains
do you have formal training and humor
writing is that something you've studied
or do you evolved through this through a
and B testing or how did you get to be
to that point you think so in my early
days it was just trial and error but
I've developed the formula a thinking
wait to sneeze in a minute so just
warning you I'll get Rosie to mark right
then but so I've
you could google this to see the details
but I wrote what I call the six
dimensions of humor and the idea is that
you have to use at least two of the six
dimensions or people who will not even
recognize it as humor mm-hmm
now I always I always falter when I'm
trying to mention the six well I'll
mention as many as I can remember for
example so clever bizarre naughty I'll
think of the others but the point is
recognizable is another one so
recognizable is probably the one you
were talking about so recognizable is if
I take Dilbert and I put them in a
situation which other people have been
in they say oh my boss does that to me
all the time I have one dimension but
then I've got to do something clever or
naughty so in other words the punchline
is something you know something heard
him in his butt or there was you know
some vague you know sexual problem
that's not specified because it's a
comic but you know there's something
there or it's a clever almost
engineering solution in the way they
shouldn't have normally worked but does
so if you put together two out of three
you've got something the best the best
cartoonists in the world would start
with two so if you look at carve Calvin
and Hobbes two of the dimensions are
acute and bizarre Calvin and Hobbes had
a cute little kid and a tiger but the
tiger was sometimes a tiger and
sometimes it was stopped so that was
bizarre plus there was kid who sometimes
talk like an adult that was bizarre
so Watterson would start with two
dimensions before he even wrote a joke
so it's not a coincidence that he had
the most you know probably the best most
people would say comic of all time
and the farside did would had the same
advantage people at people I did a
little tweet a little tweets that I'm
going to talk to Scott any questions for
him and one of the questions that came
up the most was did have you ever met
Watterson and now he is famous as a
recluse and neither of us have ever made
an attempt to meet the other
um I have this thing this mic my kids
they tell me oh I send memes back and
forth we have this whole collection of
memes while we do all day send each
other memes memes memes memes names
names now I understand memes to be an
idea but it seems to me
memes it being changed for the word
comic now they're like one panel comics
is there a relationship there or am I am
I missing that well the memes usually
have a message yeah whereas comics
sometimes are just trying to be funny
I think the meme is usually has a
utility or a function so you're trying
to mock somebody you don't like to
reduce their power so there's always
something you're trying to accomplish
with a meme that a comic is just
entertain interesting are the most
interesting entertaining comics ones
that do have a message in them though
like something or now well it depends
you know in Dilbert comics I owe the
message that's sort of embedded in a lot
of it is that management is silly and
people are irrational and you know we do
things for the wrong reasons we don't
know why we're doing it but that's not
so much a social message yeah if you
tried to put tried to be too preachy in
a comic I don't think it would work so
the you bring a subtext is really
important and humor right it's the
message that gets transmitted that's not
over and the messaging do you think
about subtext when you're crafting your
tweets and such or do you just sort of
you have like I imagine you're just so
experienced now that you can just fire
them off the subtext comes out on its
own or do you ever do you have a system
or a process for that do you ever think
subtext first and then how do i how do i
express that or i've done it in every
direction but the most common direction
that's 95% of the time i would say is
that i start with a situation so
something happens usually it's something
in the real world that could happen to
somebody that's so I get one dimension
so I want to nail the first dimension
this like oh you had that happen to me
and the second dimension could be
anything and if I and if I can add a
third dimension then it's going to be a
home run so it's usually I just built it
from situation what layer is automatic
and then what layer can I add to it it's
fascinating to me how there is actual
system an actual system to being funny
you you go to watch a comedian do
stand-up and because the good ones are
so good at it it feels like also when
you're reading a book feels like they're
just sitting there talking to you
they're just riffing and but really it's
such an asymmetric experience right I
read your book and frankly I find your
writing to just be so accessible it's so
clear it's it's fantastic and it's not
caught up in trying to sound fancy or
anything which in and of itself is a
fanciness that most people can't grasp
clarity is very difficult but it's such
an asymmetric experience your book was
written in a draft and ran out on and
then a draft and then a draft another
draft it was edited and revised I've
done it a ton for every paragraph you
know there's 50 paragraphs that went
before it and but when you're reading it
it's like it just an instantaneous flow
have you ever reflected upon that and is
there any sort of relevance in sort of
the way I don't really know where I'm
going that so they're just to make this
observation is that the best sort of
writing and communication seems simple
and clear but yet there's like an army
of work that went behind it yeah very
interesting relationship between creator
and consumer very asymmetric and it's
the effort that you have to put in so
one of the reasons that I added
persuasion to my tellers stack is that
as a writer it makes all of your writing
more accessible so learning to write
simple direct sentences is really about
understanding how the brain works and
the cleanest example that is if I said
you have a choice of these two sentences
you're going to write about and the
first one is the the ball was hit by the
boy and then the second sentence which
means exactly the same thing the boy the
boy hit the ball yeah now if I say to an
on writer which of those is the right
way they might say well I've heard that
a direct sentence is better but
basically they say the same thing
so I'd say they're about equal yeah and
here's what the persuader knows that
your brain is wired to
want to hear this the person first the
boy now I've imagined a boy now tell me
what the boy is doing he's hitting a
ball if you do it the other way the
brain has to work harder the ball was
hit by what what okay the boy now I have
to play it in Reverse because now I know
who started it and then I can replay it
so it's twice as much work to process
the ball was hit by the boy compared to
the boy at the ball once you learn all
of those simple little wiring truths
about a brain you learn things like we
only remember 10% of what we experienced
you know I could go on but and and if
you if you make a long sentence people
are just gonna get bored and tired and
they're gonna wonder why it was so long
so I just don't and it also people don't
process adjectives and adverbs so if you
were gonna write something let's say in
a business context and you wrote it was
very hot yesterday well when you write
it you say to yourself I need to say
very hot because I want them to know
like it's not just ah eighty degrees
it's very hot well but what the
persuader and the and a good writer
knows is that that person's doctor
remember the word very right they'll
remember it was hot so you can you can
just get rid of all the words that
people aren't going to remember after
they've read it and and then it becomes
clean and simple yeah and as a reader
you can tell when you hit a passage that
isn't hasn't been well done because your
eyes start to skip over the words a
little bit and then you're like you
start think about something else and
you're like oh why did I just read a
paragraph I don't even I don't even know
what I read that this the best advice I
ever got was just strong nouns strong
verbs and if you can just remember that
it sounds so simple but yet people screw
it up all the time everywhere you go
there's so much trash writing out there
that you would think that nobody had
ever heard that simple principle ever in
their whole life why is it so hard to
write so simply Scott well I think if
you take a writing class in college they
teach you to write complicated yes
there's some sense that it has to be
sort of academic and a certain
vocabulary etc but the the genius of
writing is to write it so everybody
knows what the words mean you know
you you and I are a professional writers
of a certain age I would say that my
vocabulary if you were to you know
compare to let's say just the average
public probably in the top one percent
just because I do this for a living you
know words or words or what I do and
still I could be reading something on
CNN website not so much CNN but just
some some article and I'll run into a
word I don't know and I think that's not
my fault
yeah it's not my fault right right so
somebody's at fault it's not me right
yeah that's it just think the bigger the
vocabulary or have you realized the less
useful it becomes a time sink because
you can't really drop those words in
there one of the things that your
influence on me has one of the you have
influenced me tremendously may use some
strong strong now strong verbs and one
of them was systems before goals and
another one all of them sort of just fit
around a mindset and then the final one
was really about thinking of mental
models of the world and and I can't
remember I think you might have been the
one to introduce me to this just that
phrase mental model of the world mental
model of the world mental model of the
world being broken and I had sort of
taken that to heart that my perceptive
tools this the the ideas I were I was
given the frame of reference I had none
of that seemed to be producing anything
that made any sense to me anymore like
I'm having trouble or has having trouble
making sense of the world do you think
our mental models that we've had up
until now are kind of broken
do they need updating desire does our
operating software need updating well I
have said that in the last few years
that our whole understanding of reality
is going to change and I think politics
have changed that because we understand
the facts don't matter anymore yeah we
just keep saying one example after
another where somebody can just make up
facts and it didn't really change
anything and and so I think that's the
biggest understanding is that we're all
living in some kind of a subjective
world now on top of that you're seeing a
big movement toward the psychedelics so
people using mushrooms and
micro dosing LSD and this sort of thing
and I think that that's further
emphasizing that reality is subjective
because if you do mushrooms for example
I'm not recommending it and just tell
you what it what it feels like it feels
like you've entered a whole different
world but yet it works
you still can take a drink of water or
you could still you know where the
bathroom is everything works but it's
like you're seeing it for the first time
yeah once you have that experience even
once you realize that the other
experience is it an interpretation and
not and not a infinitely accurate view
of the world and where are you getting
evidence that people are more interested
in psychedelics than they were before I
mean my first thought was like 60s and
and the electric kool-aid acid test that
seemed like a real phenomenon is that
really is this is this just like among
your friends out there in the West Coast
out here in DC I don't hear anybody
talking about that oh yeah in Silicon
Valley
probably everybody beyond a certain
level successes has done some kind of
psychedelics and it probably does about
a regular basis it's as it's as common
as as drinking probably and so it might
be different here but what I was talking
about actually was the medical
therapeutic uses because there there are
people who are experiencing breaking you
know alcohol and opioid addictions after
one dose of low dose of like psilocybin
or of LSD or something yeah and several
of those psychedelics have the same
therapeutic value apparently so you're
seeing you know the laws are loosening
up in some places you see more talk of
legalizing more talk of testing more
studies coming out I would say in five
years here's my prediction in five years
the the most common treatment for
alcoholism and addiction will be a
psychedelic in five years that's
interesting I have a lot of personal
experience with psychedelics I've
experimented with mushrooms and MDMA
especially back in the 90s for sure and
I will say without any doubt my
experience with MDMA or ecstasy or Molly
or whatever
they're calling it these days completely
transform my ideas of reality and
enhance my senses of empathy made me
feel connected to other people in a way
that I hadn't ordinarily and
interestingly enough it was those
experiences that really solidified me to
think I was on the left to think that I
was liberal and loved everybody and and
became much more accepting of everyone
and have just a variety of experiences
you know of course we're hanging out
with people from the fringes at that
time of society so it was sort of like a
twilight space of culture you know like
the right before sunset and that weird
glow and it was just a I would highly
recommend it but I don't really
recommend it what can't recommend you do
drugs on this podcast but it was hugely
influential on me and I know it was
influential on you and even in your your
persuasion book list where I think there
were references to people that like
maybe was Timothy Leary on there I don't
know it's just sort of the experience of
opening your mind using drugs to
alternate realities would you prescribe
no you're not going to prescribe do you
think that those types of experiences
are essential to understanding just sort
of the environment that we live in and
this the the experience that we're
having in this universe well almost
everybody who goes through these
experiences says the same thing which is
okay it's I'm forever different now that
and that's not like having a drink yeah
yeah you can get pretty drunk and you're
the same person after you're sober but
you loosen again you do a loosen to gin
once and your whole worldview will
change and it won't go back so that's
the big difference yeah that's
interesting I doubt that our nation or
maybe we'll ever have widely accepted
this notion that everybody needs to take
a trip into its corner to come yeah let
me just for the purpose of safety yeah
there's not there's nothing I've
mentioned that I think is a good idea
without medical supervision and see if
you have some underlying mental issues
or you're on other kinds of drugs it's
some dangerous stuff so don't do this
lightly but I think the medical world
will embrace this within five years
you know we've done a little bit over an
hour here and I have a few more
questions and and one of them is I
appreciate you coming on the podcast my
question to you is why why did you and
not me in particular but why do you why
are you so accessible to people who are
looking to interview you alternate media
like this what what is it about how does
that fit into your game plan Scott well
of course I always have a book out that
I'm promoting so the latest is loser
think and I decided that after seeing
lots of regular media hits and then I'll
watch you know what happens to the book
sales and then you go on James Altucher
right that panel you know it explodes
yeah and yeah he's just one example but
podcasts are the the new most legitimate
way to for an author to to get known
because there's two-minute hits on CNN
or Fox News don't tell you anything they
just put your face out there yeah
interesting well I can appreciate that
but it's also just a for me personally
I've been doing other people's podcast
now because I find a I just need
practice talking and I just like enjoy
actually talking to people I always
leave these conversations feeling more
energetic than beforehand I gotta say
Scott I was a little nervous for this
one that's not good persuasion but I was
a little nervous and I used one of your
tricks to calm me down a little bit but
I was very excited at this opportunity
to sit down with you because truly I for
my world changed dramatically 2015
onwards after I got onto Twitter I mean
if my friend Mike and I have been
friends since five years before he even
got on Twitter like I was I was in
Mike's wedding like I've known him way
before any of this stuff happens so I
followed him onto Twitter and I didn't
know what the hell I was getting into or
what was gonna happen to my life but
like my life is completely totally 100%
different than it was then completely
new professional career completely new
social life completely new perspective
on the world and you know you were you
were definitely a part of that and your
books have been a part of that and I
just want to say thank you first of all
for putting some great ideas into my
head and for sort of leading the way in
this new medium and being like a real
sort of torch bearer for this new system
of communication which is still even
though it feels like it's been around
for a little bit it's still like totally
in its infancy this this new way of us
communicating is just brand new and in a
you know historical sense it's all just
began immediately right now we don't
even know where it's gonna go or what
it's going to do and you're effectively
a pioneer so it's a it's been fun to
watch and I really appreciate that on
this journey for you what has been the
highlight of becoming a social media
star and and what has become what was
become the what was the law and if you
knew then what you know now would you
have still done it the answer is yes I
would still do it I would say the the
low points or any day that there's some
you know scurrilous rumor about me and
the the paid trolls come in by the
thousands and make my life miserable for
a while and mostly it's just
inconvenience I don't like taking all
the time to block them all so it's just
taking my time but for some reason most
of the professional trolls let have left
me alone for the last month and I don't
know why but they all just disappeared
which also tells you they're organized
there are organized if anybody is
listening to this who doesn't know both
both sides left and right have organized
troll armies you don't always know who's
controlling them but you know when they
arrive because they'll they all say the
same thing and they arrive at the same
time so that those are all bad days the
best day by far and I think Twitter had
a lot to do with it was getting invited
to the Oval Office to chat with the
president just because he was it was
working his his supporters basically and
and that was by far I think will be my
coolest life experience yeah just just
go in there being in the Oval Office
talking to the President of the United
States about whatever we wanted to talk
about for about half an hour
I'm never gonna be able to match that as
an experience yeah Wow a half an hour
man that's pretty good it wasn't just a
handshake in the line or whatever that's
awesome that's awesome well
congratulations on that congratulations
on your success the latest book loser
think what is and what were the last
couple was win big Lee was one before
that right and what that was how to fail
at almost everything FATA failed almost
everything and still win big and still
win big all of which have a certain
self-help element to them and I wonder
Scott inside of you there there's
somebody that wants to help people isn't
that right yeah primarily I often
describe the perfect life arc as being
born as a baby and you're perfectly
selfish because you can't do anything
for yourself anyway then we get a little
older and maybe can help out around the
house by the time you're an adult and a
parent you're probably doing more for
your kids and your job and your spouse
and you are for yourself and by the time
you die if you've done everything right
your last moment you know as the life is
extinguished from your body you
literally give up everything you've
accumulated you you're right you just
give it all up so your last moment of
life and as you transition is the
ultimate unselfish act you give away
everything and but and ideally you've
you've left good ideas and influence and
and an advice so I thought well I'm an
author why don't I put this in a book
you know I will boost my signal and I
thought I had things to say but you
don't really know until the books out
there and people respond to it and after
I wrote I had a fail I mean it was just
wildly successful and people still talk
to me everyday people say I lost 80
pounds I got off of drugs I got a job I
got a promotion based on stuff from the
book so that that kind of encourages you
to do more because you know monetarily
it doesn't make that much difference to
me these days but having that influence
and seeing people's lives improve I mean
that's a really big payback I mean
that's just deeply deeply satisfying it
really is and you should be commended
for that and I wish the people that gave
you so much hassle online would realize
that deep deep inside not even
very much on the surface is somebody
that is really just trying to help
people out and is trying to spread good
information useful things that's gonna
lead to direct improvements in people's
lives and I can say I'm one of those
people and I can say that some of those
concepts
I have also now leveraged up into
influencing other people myself and so
there's an exponential effect to it so
thank you for that thank you for coming
on the show I really appreciate it
thanks for being a good sport and
answering some of the some of the
questions honestly I really appreciate
that to Scott and you know just keep on
doing what you're doing and I'll keep
watching and thank you very much thanks
jack thanks for having me and good luck
with everything all right thanks a lot I
appreciate it
[Music]
you